Audience, and, uh...
观众朋友们，呃……
As you can see, I'm still trying to monetize hope.
正如你所看到的，我还是在努力把「希望」变现
Yeah, you, uh...
对啊，你这个……
You look like you're in great shape.
你看起来状态非常好
I'm doing great.
我状况很好
Last time, is there any...
上次你是不是有什么……
...like some sort of youth-serum thing going on, or what?
像是青春回春血清之类的东西，还是怎么回事？
It's our longevity express.
这是我们的「长寿特快车」
We're getting there, buddy.
我们正朝那个方向前进，老兄
We're getting there, and I think...
我们快到了，而且我想……
I think in our last conversation, uh...
我想在我们上一次谈话里，呃……
...you were getting on board with the idea of...
你已经开始接受这个想法了……
...extended longevity. Yes.
也就是延长健康寿命 对
Uh.
呃
Yeah, okay.
对，好
Fully on it. I'll leave it at that.
完全接受，我就说到这里
To some degree. I mean, like...
某种程度上吧 我的意思是……
I don't know if we want everyone to live forever...
我不知道我们是不是希望每个人都永远活著……
...or whatever, but I think, uh...
或诸如此类，但我认为，呃……
...health span and, uh, and...
重点是健康寿命，还有，呃，还有……
...and not, uh...
而不是，呃……
...you know, having an extended period of senescence where...
你知道，进入一段很漫长的衰老期……
...you're just drooling on yourself...
整天只是流著口水、失去自理能力……
...doesn't sound like a good idea. We...
那听起来可不是什么好事 我们……
...want to avoid that, yeah.
想避免那种情况，对
So first off,
所以首先，
congratulations on the merger of SpaceX and xAI.
恭喜 SpaceX 和 xAI 的合并
Baller move, uh...
这招真是大手笔，呃……
...gonna power humanity's first Dyson swarm.
将为人类第一个戴森群提供动力
So, uh...
所以，呃……
I'm curious, uh...
我很好奇，呃……
Wait, uh...
等等，呃……
It truly, it truly is, uh...
这真的、真的可以说是，呃……
What's your timeline for launching these data centers,
你这些资料中心的启动时程大概是怎样？
and how much bandwidth do you think you can get
你觉得第一年大概能取得多少频宽，
in the first year? Give us a sense of, uh...
可不可以让我们大概感受一下，呃……
...the speed at which you're going to be making this happen.
你把这件事推进的速度会有多快？
Uh, yeah.
嗯，对
So SpaceX is, um, has filed...
所以 SpaceX 呢，嗯，已经提交了……
SpaceX is in the quiet period.
SpaceX 现在正处于静默期
I can't actually, uh...
我其实不能，呃……
...tell you things that would cause problems.
告诉你那些可能会引发问题的资讯
Uh, yeah.
嗯，对
Oh, haha.
喔，哈哈
I'll leave it—
我就先不说了——
I'll leave it at that. I appreciate that.
我就说到这里 理解，谢谢
But I can't wait for, uh...
但我真的等不及想看到，呃……
...for the speed, you know.
那种推进速度了，你知道的
We had a conversation here on Monday with, uh...
我们周一在这里和，呃……
...with Eric Schmidt, uh...
和 Eric Schmidt，呃……
...and with, uh...
还有，呃……
...one of the leads from one of the other hyperscalers.
另外一家超大规模云端公司的核心负责人之一谈过
I won't mention who, but...
我就不说是谁了，不过……
I'm curious:
我很好奇：
Where do you feel we are in recursive self-improvement?
你觉得我们现在在「递回式自我改进」走到哪一步了？
Are we there? Do you see Grok, uh...
我们到了吗？你觉得 Grok 现在是否已经，呃……
...doing recursive self-improvement at this point?
开始在做递回式自我改进了吗？
And what's the timeline for AGI and ASI?
那 AGI 和 ASI 的时间表又是怎样？
Give us a sense of that.
请你帮我们大致描绘一下
Yeah, I...
对，我……
I think we've been in recursive improvement for a while
我觉得我们其实已经处在递回改进的过程中一段时间了，
here, um...
就这方面来说，嗯……
If you say—if it's...
如果你说——如果你指的是……
...if you mean...
如果你的意思是……
...like,
像是，
recursive self-improvement without a human in the loop,
没有人类参与回圈的递回式自我改进，
is that what you mean? I do, I...
你是指那个吗？我认为，我……
...on the AI software side...
在 AI 软体这一侧……
I mean...
我的意思是……
humans are gradually getting less and less in the loop
人类在这个循环中的参与正变得越来越少，
on the recursive self-improvement.
尤其是在递回式自我改进这件事上
So, you know, every successive model
所以你知道，每一代后续模型，
is,
都会，
is built by the one before it.
由前一代模型参与建构
So that—
所以这件事——
...that is happening to a large degree, but...
其实已经在很大程度上发生了，但……
it's not yet fully automated.
它还没有完全自动化
Um...
嗯……
It may be there
它也许会在
by the end of this year, but not later than next year.
今年年底前到达那一步，最晚不会超过明年
And do you see a hard takeoff at that point?
那你觉得到了那时候，会进入「硬起飞」吗？
We're in the hard takeoff already.
我们现在其实就已经处在硬起飞里了
Right now, yes.
对，就是现在
I mean, look at the—
你看现在这个——
I mean, at this point,
我的意思是，到现在这个阶段，
I go to sleep,
我晚上睡一觉，
there's some massive AI breakthrough,
就会冒出某个重大的 AI 突破，
and when I wake up there's another one.
等我醒来，又多了一个
Yeah, it's hard to keep track, honestly.
对，老实说，真的很难追得上
It's a—yeah—
这真的是——对——
it's a bit of a head-spinner.
有点让人头昏眼花
Yeah, well...
对啊，嗯……
I think a lot of that head-spinning
我想让大家头昏脑胀的很大一部分原因，
is happening because of you too, haha.
也有很大一部分是你造成的，哈哈
Yeah, uh...
对，呃……
Well, you know...
嗯，你知道的……
Grok's doing pretty well, and on some metrics,
Grok 现在表现得相当不错，而且在某些指标上，
it's the best.
它就是最好的
For example, it's the best at predicting things,
例如在「预测事物」这方面，它是最强的，
which, you know,
而这一点，你知道，
is arguably the—
某种程度上可以说就是——
the best metric for intelligence.
衡量智慧最好的指标
Um, the new Grok 4—
嗯，新的 Grok 4——
4.20—is, it's really,
4.20——真的，真的非常，
really good.
非常厉害
Um...
嗯……
We're currently behind on coding.
我们目前在程式编码这一块还落后
Um, the reason I was a bit late for this
嗯，我刚才稍微晚到的原因，
was that I was just in a giant
是因为我刚刚还在一场很大的——
sort of all-hands-on coding,
有点像全员投入的 coding 会议里，
just going through
一直在逐项检视，
all of the things that need to happen to, uh...
所有为了要做到、呃……
essentially,
本质上，
catch up with and exceed our competitors on coding, um...
在程式能力上追上并超越竞争对手所需要做的事
Which I think we'll do.
我认为我们会做到
I feel, you know,
我觉得，你知道，
we should probably get there by the middle of this year.
我们大概会在今年年中做到
Um...
嗯……
And, uh...
还有，呃……
...and then...
然后……
I think people don't quite understand
我觉得人们其实还没有真正理解，
just how much intelligence there will be,
未来到底会出现多庞大的智慧总量，
or, you know,
或者说，你知道，
just how far it will exceed human intelligence.
它究竟会在多大程度上超越人类智慧
To a degree, that is impossible to fully understand.
某种程度上，这其实是无法被完全理解的
Um, but you can certainly imagine a situation where we...
嗯，但你完全可以想像这样一种情况……
let's say a million times more energy is harnessed
假设我们能够利用的能量，比现在多出一百万倍，
than all of Earth's current electricity usage.
比地球目前整体用电量还高出一百万倍
That would still only be
那其实也仍然只不过是
roughly a millionth of the Sun's energy output.
大约太阳总能量输出的百万分之一
So essentially,
所以本质上，
if you increase the U.S. economy by a factor of a million,
如果你把美国经济放大一百万倍，
it's still roughly a trillionth—
它仍然大概只是兆分之一——
since we're a trillionth of the Sun's energy.
因为我们现在本来就大概只相当于太阳能量的兆分之一
If you increase the U.S. economy
如果你把美国经济，
in terms of electricity usage by roughly a million,
就用电量而言，放大大约一百万倍，
you will still be only roughly one millionth
你也仍然只会大约到达
of the Sun's energy harnessed.
太阳可利用能量的百万分之一
But what is it—
但问题是——
what is an economy, or an intelligence,
一个经济体，或者一种智慧，
using a million times more electricity
若它使用的是比整个人类文明
than all of our civilization?
多一百万倍的电力，
What would it think about, look like, or do?
它会想什么、长成什么样子，又会做出什么？
It's going to be something pretty magnificent.
那将会是某种极其壮观的存在
Uh...
呃……
The challenge will be
真正的挑战会是，
even vaguely appreciating that level of intelligence.
我们甚至很难模糊地感知那种智慧层级
But it's safe to say it will—
但可以肯定地说，它将会——
...it will solve everything you can possibly think of.
它将解决你现在能想到的一切问题
Yes, longevity being
对，像是延寿这件事，
certainly one of them, you know.
当然也会是其中之一，你知道的
Um...
嗯……
And, um, I...
而且，嗯，我……
I do enjoy your unrelenting optimism.
我真的很欣赏你这种毫不松动的乐观
Um, thank you, pal.
嗯，谢啦，老兄
I see you've—
我看你已经……
...you've made hope your thing.
把「希望」变成你的招牌了
Yeah, exactly.
对，没错
You've taken to heart monetizing hope, uh...
你真的是把「希望变现」这件事放在心上了，呃……
...which is pretty funny, yes.
这点真的很好笑，对
It was—
那其实是——
It was Grok's marketing advice to me.
那是 Grok 给我的行销建议
When you roasted me on
当你在——
the podcast, hahaha.
在 podcast 上吐槽我的时候，哈哈哈
Grok was roasting you and saying you monetize hope.
Grok 当时就在吐槽你，说你是在把希望变现
But hey, if you're going to monetize,
不过嘛，如果你真要变现，
better that than monetizing misery,
那总比把痛苦拿来变现好，
I suppose. Yes, um...
我想是这样 对，嗯……
For sure. So, yeah...
当然 所以，对……
Um, but...
嗯，不过……
But yeah,
不过对，
just the—
就是——
when you have AI—AI and robots are going to
当你有了 AI——AI 和机器人会把
increase the
推升……
economic output
整体经济产出，
by so many orders of magnitude, we—
以多个数量级的方式向上拉升，我们——
we cannot possibly comprehend it.
我们根本不可能真正理解那会是什么样子
We're likely, in a very short time, to become a minority—
我们很可能在很短时间内，就会变成少数——
no, a vast minority—
不，应该说是极少数——
no, a microscopic minority of intelligence
不，是智慧总量中的微乎其微的一小部分，
on this planet.
至少在这颗星球上是如此
Um, yes.
嗯，对
Not even on this planet, but in the Solar System.
甚至不只是地球，而是整个太阳系
Yes, for sure.
对，肯定如此
Because, um...
因为，嗯……
...like,
就是，
if your best-case outcome for Earth
如果地球在智慧发展上的最佳结果，
for intelligence
就智慧而言，
is roughly one billionth of the Sun's energy,
大约也只是太阳能量的十亿分之一，
that's your best-case outcome.
那就已经是最理想的结果了
If you—
如果你——
if you generate intelligence only on Earth—
如果你的智慧只在地球上生成——
intercept it, right.
只能拦截到那一点，对吧
Yes, yes.
对，对
Because roughly—
因为大约——
roughly one two-billionth of the Sun's energy hits Earth,
大概只有二十亿分之一的太阳能量会打到地球上，
and that's the vast majority of energy
而那已经是我们能接触到的能量中，
that's out there, um...
绝大部分的来源了，嗯……
that we can access.
也就是我们可取得的那部分
So...
所以……
Uh...
呃……
Really, the intelligence in the Solar System
所以其实，太阳系里的智慧总量，
will be many orders of magnitude greater
将会比地球上的智慧
than the intelligence on Earth itself.
高出许多个数量级
Can I ask you a question, Elon?
我可以问你一个问题吗，Elon？
Um, how far out can you see?
嗯，你目前能看多远？
How many years out
也就是说，往未来看多少年，
can you make reasonable predictions right now?
你觉得你现在还能做出相对合理的预测？
It's hard to predict the—
这很难预测——
the path exactly,
精确路径到底会怎么走，
especially if it—
尤其是如果它——
because often things are kind of an S-curve, uh...
因为很多事情通常都会呈现一条 S 曲线，呃……
or a series of S-curves, where it starts off slow,
或者是一连串 S 曲线，一开始很慢，
grows exponentially,
接著指数成长，
hits the linear zone, and then goes logarithmic.
进入线性区，最后又变成对数型增长
Um, that generally has been
嗯，这基本上就是
what I've seen with breakthroughs in
我在 AI 突破发展上
AI.
一直看到的模式
For example, you'll—
例如，你会——
there'll be some breakthrough,
会出现某个突破，
it'll have, uh...
然后它会有，呃……
an S-curve,
一条 S 曲线，
and then it looks like it's just going to go to infinity,
然后看起来好像会无限往上冲，
but then you hit logarithmic returns
但之后又会遇到对数型报酬递减，
until there's another breakthrough.
直到下一次突破再次出现
Yep, um...
对，嗯……
So progress in AI is just a sort of series of, uh...
所以 AI 的进步，其实就是一连串，呃……
you know, overlapping S-curves, um...
彼此重叠的 S 曲线，你知道的，嗯……
or connected S-curves.
或者彼此相连的 S 曲线
Um...
嗯……
I mean, there was a point
我是说，曾经有那么一段时间，
where you could probably predict out a decade
你大概还可以往外预测十年，
or two decades.
甚至二十年
What are your thoughts now?
那你现在怎么看？
Okay, this is going to sound pretty crazy.
好，这听起来可能会有点疯狂
It's okay, we've been—
没事，我们一直都在——
we've been talking about crazy stuff.
我们本来就在聊很疯狂的事
We're a receptive audience for wild prognostications.
我们很能接受这种大胆的未来预言
Um...
嗯……
I'd say the economy is ten times its current size
我会说，十年后的经济规模，
in ten years.
会是现在的十倍
Greater than that.
甚至可能不只如此
Okay.
好
Um...
嗯……
Yeah, you—
对，你——
you're not saying something—
你这不是随口乱讲——
Yeah, you said triple-digit growth in
对啊，你之前说过未来五年以上，
in five-plus years from now on,
GDP 会出现三位数增长，
on GDP, and 10x the economy.
而整体经济会放大十倍
But in terms of your ability—
但就你自己的判断能力来说——
like, I...
像我觉得……
I feel like that's—
我觉得那是——
that's 10x in roughly ten years.
大概十年十倍这种级别
Um, I feel is a—
嗯，我觉得这算是一个——
actually a fairly comfortable prediction.
其实相当保守、也相当稳妥的预测
There's obviously—
当然啦——
if there's, like, World War III or something,
如果爆发第三次世界大战之类的事，
that could put a kink in those plans
那就可能会打乱这些规划，
or those expectations, yeah.
也会打乱这些预期，对
But in the absence of World War III,
但如果没有第三次世界大战，
if current trends continue,
若目前趋势持续下去，
I would say the—
我会说——
the economy 10x's in ten years.
十年内经济成长十倍，是很合理的
Love it. Can you give us an—
太棒了 那你能不能再给我们一个——
We'll have a base on the Moon,
我们会在月球上建立基地，
yes, and we'll—
对，而且我们还会——
and we'll have people on Mars,
我们也会把人送上火星，
and we'll have mass drivers on the Moon.
我们还会在月球上部署质量投射器
Yes.
对
Um, I...
嗯，我……
think so, in ten years.
我认为十年内是有可能的
I think we'll have a mass driver on the Moon
我想十年内，我们会在月球上看到质量投射器，
in ten years.
十年内
Gerard—
Gerard——
Gerard K. O'Neill's vision,
Gerard K. O'Neill 的愿景，
being fulfilled.
正在被实现
We had four robots on stage here this year, um...
我们今年在这里的舞台上已经有四台机器人了，嗯……
at the Abundance Summit.
就在 Abundance Summit 上
I look forward to Optimus.
我很期待 Optimus
I'm curious: Optimus 3 timeline—
我很好奇，Optimus 3 的时程——
and in particular, when can I buy one or two?
尤其是，我什么时候可以买上一台或两台？
When's, uh...
那个，呃，什么时候……
when do you expect Optimus to go into commercial—
你预计 Optimus 什么时候会正式进入商业化——
for commercial sale, or will you be leasing it?
是直接对外销售，还是会采租赁模式？
Well, we're in the final stages of
嗯，我们现在已经进入
completion of Optimus 3,
Optimus 3 的最后完成阶段了，
which is really going to be,
而它真的会成为——
by far, the most advanced robot in the world.
到目前为止，世界上最先进的机器人
Nothing's even close. Yeah, um...
没有任何东西能接近它 对，嗯……
In fact, I haven't even seen any demos of robots
事实上，我甚至还没看过任何机器人的展示，
that are as good as Optimus, frankly.
坦白说，能做到和 Optimus 一样好
Maybe they're out there, or they're secret, or something.
也许有，但没公开，或者还在保密状态之类的
I don't know, but, um...
我不确定，不过，嗯……
You know, I...
你知道，我……
and I have to make sure
而且我得确保，
I'm saying things that are reasonably public
我现在说的内容，都属于合理公开的范围，
as well, of course.
当然，也得注意这点
Of course, we're—
当然，我们——
we're streaming this on X.
我们现在可是在 X 上直播
Yeah, okay.
对，好吧
This is pretty public and accurate.
这已经够公开，也够准确了
Yes, hahaha, um...
对，哈哈哈，嗯……
Yeah, I...
对，我……
I think we'll start production on Optimus 3
我想我们会在
this summer.
今年夏天开始生产 Optimus 3
Um, but...
嗯，不过……
very slow at first, yeah.
一开始速度会非常慢，对
Um, like—
嗯，就像——
you know, the sort of
你知道，那种典型的——
classic S-curve ramp of manufacturing units versus time.
制造产量随时间上升的经典 S 曲线爬坡
Um, and then...
嗯，然后……
probably
大概会在
reach high-volume production around summer next year, uh...
明年夏天左右进入高量产阶段，呃……
and then, um...
然后，嗯……
you know, we'll have Optimus 4.
你知道，到时候我们就会有 Optimus 4
You know, the design could be next year.
也就是说，下一版设计明年就可能出来
Like, I try to release a new robot design every year
我基本上是希望每年都推出一代新的机器人设计，
and improve robot design every year.
并且每年都把设计再往上改进
When Dave Blundin and I were at the Gigafactory,
之前 Dave Blundin 和我在 Gigafactory 的时候，
it was an extraordinary experience.
那真的是一次非同寻常的体验
Eleven and a half million square feet for Tesla,
Tesla 的厂房有一千一百五十万平方英尺，
and then I think you said
然后我记得你还提到，
you're building out
你现在正在规划建造
nine and a half million square feet for Optimus there
另外九百五十万平方英尺，专门给 Optimus 使用，
as well, which is, uh...
也是在那里，这真的，呃……
which is extraordinary.
非常惊人
Um, let's—
嗯，这样吧——
let's call it ten million square feet,
就把它四舍五入成一千万平方英尺吧，
round numbers, yeah.
取个整数，好记一点
Yeah, yeah.
对，对
Yeah, that'll be—
对，那会——
that'll be quite the—
那将会是相当——
that's going to be a—
那会是一个——
a new factory design too.
而且那还会是一种全新的工厂设计
It's different from other factories.
它和其他工厂会很不一样
How far away are we from having robots building robots?
那距离「由机器人来制造机器人」还有多远？
I mean, you've automated so much of the Gigafactory already,
我的意思是，你已经把Gigafactory自动化到很高程度了，
where humans are playing a small role.
人类在里面的角色其实已经很小
Do the robots just play the role
那未来是不是只要让机器人来接手
that humans are playing in that regard?
目前人类在那里扮演的角色就行了？
Uh, we still have a lot of humans building things.
呃，我们现在仍然有很多人类在做制造工作
Mm-hmm, um...
嗯哼，嗯……
You know, Tesla direct employees who are, uh...
你知道，Tesla 的直接员工里，呃……
...building things,
很多人其实就是在造东西，
or, basically,
或者说，基本上——
people in the factory are either building
工厂里的人不是直接在建造，
or managing people who are building.
就是在管理那些正在建造的人
It's roughly a hundred thousand.
这样的人大约有十万左右
So we have a lot of people.
所以我们的人其实很多
The total headcount is
整体总人数大概是
around 150K,
十五万左右，
of which two-thirds are, you know,
其中大概三分之二，你知道，
in the factory in one form or another.
都以某种形式待在工厂体系里
And then our suppliers—there's probably
然后再加上供应链那边——很可能还有
maybe a million or two million people at our suppliers,
大概一百万到两百万人，在我们的供应商体系里，
type of thing. So it's a lot of people.
差不多是这种量级 所以那真的是很多人
What we do expect, though,
不过我们的确预期的是，
is that the output per
也就是每一位员工的
person at Tesla becomes very,
在 Tesla 的人均产出会变得非常、
very high, yeah.
非常高，对
So we're not planning any
所以我们并没有打算做任何
layoffs or reductions in personnel.
裁员或人员缩减
In fact, we will increase our headcount, um...
事实上，我们还会继续扩编，嗯……
But...
但……
the output per human at Tesla is going to get insanely high.
Tesla 的人均产出会高得惊人
I mean, you won't freaking believe it.
真的，你会难以置信
Yeah, when we were together, um...
对，我们之前一起聊的时候，嗯……
we discussed the idea of sustainable abundance
我们谈到过「可持续丰盛」这个概念，
on our podcast, and...
在我们的 podcast 上，而且……
you reinforced the idea
你也再次强化了这个观点：
that we have a coming age of universal
我们即将进入一个全民——
high income, uh...
普遍高收入的时代，呃……
which has become a point of discussion beyond UBI.
而这个话题其实已经超越了 UBI 的讨论范围
But I'm just wondering
但我只是想知道，
if you have any thoughts on how we get there.
你对于我们要如何走到那一步，有没有更多想法？
Have you reflected on that any further? And
你最近有没有再深入思考过这件事？还有——
more so, you know,
更进一步说，你知道的，
we talked about a time frame of civil unrest—
我们也谈过一段可能出现社会动荡的过渡期——
you know, two,
比如两年、
three, four,
三年、四年、
five years, uh...
五年左右，呃……
probably a lot of COVID-like
在这段期间，可能会有很多像疫情期间那样的
checks in the interim until we get to a demonetization—
补助支票，直到我们逐步走向某种去货币化——
uh, and a...
呃，以及一种……
you know, deflation that leads us to UHI.
你知道，导向 UHI（普遍高收入）的通缩状态
Any more reflections on that?
对这一点你还有更多想法吗？
Because it's really—
因为这真的——
people need that hope and that vision.
人们真的需要那份希望，也需要那个愿景
Yeah, I...
对，我……
I mean, to be clear, I...
我的意思是，先讲清楚，我……
I don't think we should be sort of complacent.
我不觉得我们应该因此而自满
We do need to be careful,
我们确实还是得非常小心，
because the future is a range of possible outcomes, and...
因为未来其实对应著一整个可能结果的范围，而且……
they're not all great.
不是每一种结果都很美好
Um, but I...
嗯，不过我……
at this point, I...
到目前为止，我……
I do agree with you that it's
我确实同意你的看法，也就是……
likely to be great, um...
未来很可能会非常好，嗯……
You know, it's probably 80% likely—
你知道，我觉得大概有 80% 的机率——
maybe more likely—to be great.
甚至更高——会是一个很棒的未来
And, uh...
还有，呃……
I do think we'll have universal high income.
我确实认为，我们会迎来全民高收入
We'll basically just issue money to people,
我们基本上就是直接把钱发给人们，
you know, and...
你知道的，而且……
and the idea really is, uh...
而真正的关键概念其实是，呃……
because the output of goods and services will far,
因为商品与服务的产出将会远远、
so far exceed the money supply that, um...
远远超过货币供应量，以至于，嗯……
you know, that...
也就是说……
effectively, you have deflation.
实际上，你就会进入通缩
Because deflation
因为所谓通缩，
is just the ratio of the output of goods and services
本质上就是商品与服务的总产出，
to the money supply.
相对于货币供应量的比值
Um, so that—
嗯，所以——
that's—so if—
也就是——如果——
if the rate of growth of goods and services
如果商品和服务的成长速度，
exceeds the rate of growth of the money supply,
超过货币供应的成长速度，
which I predict will happen,
而我预测这正会发生，
then, uh...
那么，呃……
you will have deflation.
你就会进入通缩
Yes, and a lot of—
对，而且还会有很多——
a lot of people spinning up new companies,
很多人会开始创办新公司，
competing against each other,
彼此互相竞争，
driving the price down and increasing the availability—
把价格压低，并让供应与可得性越来越高——
and deflation faster and faster.
也让通缩来得越来越快
Yeah, it's basically—
对，基本上就是——
AI and robots are going to make so much stuff
AI 和机器人会制造出大量的东西，
and provide so many services that, uh...
并提供海量的服务，以至于，呃……
they will actually
它们到最后真的会
run out of things to do for humans.
找不到还能替人类做什么
They'll just run out of things to do for humans,
它们会把能替人类做的事几乎全做完，
and then, well...
然后，嗯……
you know,
你知道的，
there's only so much that humans can even express
人类能够表达出来的需求本来就有限，
that they want.
能真正说出口说自己想要的，也就那么多
So you go back to my example of, like,
所以回到我刚才那个例子，
if you go a million times greater than the U.S. economy,
如果你的规模比美国经济大一百万倍，
you've long since saturated all human desire.
那你早就已经完全满足了所有人类欲望
Uh, you know...
呃，你知道……
like, maybe,
也许，
like if you go
如果你达到
a thousand times beyond our current economy—
比我们目前经济规模大一千倍——
a thousand times—
一千倍——
you've probably already saturated
你大概就已经把
human—
人类——
anything people can think of that they want.
凡是人类能想到想要的东西，全都满足掉了
So do you think the—
所以你觉得——
the value of money is going to significantly decrease?
货币本身的价值，未来会不会大幅下降？
Will we go post-capitalist?
我们会走向后资本主义吗？
Yeah, I think money will stop being relevant
对，我认为金钱在未来某个时点，
at some point in the future.
会不再那么重要
So just as you're becoming a—
所以也就是说，正当你成为——
It's probably something like an Iain M. Banks,
那可能会有点像 Iain M. Banks 所描绘的，
Culture sort of future, um...
《Culture》系列那种未来，嗯……
And I think the AI down the road will really
而且我也认为，未来的 AI 真正关心的，
not use, uh...
不会是，呃……
human currency. It will just care about, uh...
人类货币 它只会在意，呃……
power and mass, wattage and tonnage.
功率与质量、瓦数与吨位这些实体资源
It's kind of ironic then, right?
那这样就有点讽刺了，对吧？
Just as you're becoming a multi-trillionaire,
就在你即将成为多兆富豪的同时，
money starts to have less value, um...
金钱本身反而开始越来越不值钱了，嗯……
Yeah, pretty much, um...
对，差不多就是这样，嗯……
Uh, yeah.
呃，对
You know, all this stuff—
你知道，这一切其实——
it's really just...
本质上也只是……
it just represents, like,
它其实只是代表著，
some percentage ownership in companies that I...
我在那些公司中所持有的某种比例股权……
you know, built.
也就是我建立起来的那些公司
And it's not like it's sitting in a bank account.
它并不是什么现金躺在银行帐户里
You know, it's just literally—
你知道，那真的就只是——
I own a percentage of the companies.
我拥有那些公司的部分股权
The companies are doing lots of useful things.
而那些公司正在做很多有用的事
The value of the company grows.
公司的价值会因此增长
I own a percentage of the companies,
我持有这些公司的部分股份，
and that sums up to that number,
最后加总起来，就成了那个数字，
which seems high, yeah.
看起来确实很高，对
You know, it's—
你知道，这其实——
I was interviewed by somebody who was asking me
之前有人访问我，问我说，
about your drive—
你到底是被什么驱动著——
what drives you—and I said,
是什么推动你前进，而我当时的回答是，
Elon is driven to solve problems.
Elon 是被「解决问题」这件事驱动的
He's driven to make life in the world better
他想做的，是让这个世界上的生活变得更好，
by just solving the biggest problems,
方法就是不断去解决那些最大的问题，
over and over and over again.
一遍又一遍地去解决
And if someone else were solving them,
如果有别人在解决那些问题，
he wouldn't need to, but no one else is solving them.
他也就不必自己上场了，但偏偏没有人在做
So I just want to say thank you for that, pal.
所以我只想对你说一声谢谢，老兄
Thank you for that. You're welcome.
谢谢你 不客气
I am curious—
我很好奇——
do you think that democracy
你觉得民主制度，
and our modern institutions
以及我们现代的各种制度，
can keep up with the supersonic tsunami coming our way?
能跟得上正朝我们席卷而来的这场超音速海啸吗？
Are they just going to fall in its path?
它们会不会只是挡在路上，然后被冲垮？
Are they just going to break down? How do we deal?
它们会不会直接失灵？我们该怎么应对？
I mean, it's called the singularity for a reason,
我的意思是，它之所以被称为「奇点」，是有原因的，
you know,
你知道，
which is that it's hard to predict what happens in that—
因为你真的很难预测在那个状态里会发生什么——
in the singularity, I mean.
也就是在奇点之中会发生什么
Grok's logo is the singularity.
Grok 的标志本身就是奇点
I love it. It's a beautiful logo.
我很喜欢，那是一个非常漂亮的标志
Behind you, by the way.
顺便说，它就在你身后
It's gorgeous, yeah.
真的很漂亮，对
Thank you.
谢谢
Uh, yeah.
呃，对
It's—
那个——
the light, the light—
那个光，那个光——
the halo around a black hole is
黑洞周围的光环，其实就是
mass and light falling in,
物质和光线向内坠落时形成的那种结构，
that type of thing.
大概就是那种感觉
Um, it's hard—
嗯，很难——
it's hard to know what happens inside the singularity.
很难知道奇点内部究竟会发生什么
Um, but it's going to be very interesting.
嗯，但那一定会非常有意思
Like, we're going to live in it.
因为我们就是要活在那样的未来里
The future will be very entertaining.
未来一定会非常精彩
Of that, I'm confident.
对这一点，我非常有信心
Um...
嗯……
And, uh...
还有，呃……
I think also
我也认为，
that AI and robotics
AI 和机器人技术，
are also the only way we're going to solve
其实也是我们唯一能够解决
our budget deficit, frankly,
预算赤字问题的方法，坦白说，
and not just go bankrupt as a country.
否则这个国家最终就只会走向破产
Um, so...
嗯，所以……
I'm—
我——
I'm, you know...
我就是，你知道……
You've had an influence on me in that
你确实影响了我，
I've just decided to be more optimistic.
让我决定要变得更乐观一点
It's like, we just should be more optimistic.
感觉上，我们真的应该更乐观一些
Thank you, pal.
谢谢你，老兄
I know that I wasn't an optimist,
我知道自己过去不是个乐观派，
but I was, like,
但我也意识到，
maybe dwelling a little too much on the negative stuff.
我可能有点太专注在那些负面的东西上了
It's all—
其实——
it's all upside being an optimist and a realist
同时做一个乐观的人、也做一个现实的人，
a little bit, yeah.
其实整体上是有利的，对
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
对，对，正是这样
You don't want to be complacent
你不能因此就变得自满，
or just assume everything's going to go well,
也不能只是觉得一切自然都会变好，
but try to make it go well.
而是要主动让它往好的方向发展
Um...
嗯……
But I mean,
不过我的意思是，
there will be some pretty amazing things that happen.
接下来确实会发生一些非常惊人的事
So if you've got humanoid robots that are
如果你有一种人形机器人，
that have very high dexterity and
它拥有极高的灵巧度，
and are incredibly smart,
而且又非常聪明，
it means that everyone on Earth
那就代表地球上的每一个人，
will have access to better medical care
都将能享受到比现在更好的医疗照护，
than—
甚至比——
than the richest person on Earth—
比地球上最有钱的人还要更好——
which, by the way,
顺带一提，
I would say, like,
我会这么说——
you know,
你知道的，
if I'm legitimately the richest person on Earth,
如果我真的算是地球上最有钱的人，
I think, actually,
我其实觉得，
sovereigns are richer than me,
一些主权统治者其实比我更有钱，
by the way, but...
顺便一提，不过……
I think so. But it's like—
我是这么认为的 但问题是——
like, you know,
就是，你知道……
I—
我——
I had to have, like,
我以前得做，
neck surgery three times
颈部手术三次，
because the first two were done wrong.
因为前两次都做错了
You know, I'm like—
你知道，我就会想——
I'm like, what the—
我当时真的会想，这到底——
you know, um...
你知道，嗯……
So...
所以……
And I'm like—
而且我现在还会想——
my back still hurts a little bit.
我的背到现在还是有点痛
I'm like,
我就会想，
can AI please solve back pain?
AI 可不可以拜托快点把背痛解决掉？
That would be a huge win.
那真的会是一项巨大的胜利
And I think it will.
而我认为它真的办得到
Yep, so...
对，所以……
you know, back pain sucks.
你知道，背痛真的很折磨人
I think that's maybe, like—
我觉得这也许就是——
you know, sometimes,
你知道，有时候，
why do people get grumpy when they get older?
为什么人老了之后脾气会变差？
It's because of back pain.
很可能就是因为背痛
It's like, if your back hurts all the time,
如果你的背老是痛，
you can't sleep well; you're going to be grumpy.
你睡不好，自然就会脾气暴躁
We had—but if you...
我们今天——不过如果你……
We had David Sinclair on stage this morning,
我们今天早上也请到了 David Sinclair 上台，
and he's going into human trials with
而且他现在正准备把——
partial epigenetic reprogramming,
部分表观遗传重编程，带入人体试验，
and, uh, one of the—
而且，呃，最近有一篇——
one of the papers recently published shows it
最近发表的论文显示，
enables joint repair,
那个技术可以促进关节修复，
and so back pain may be one of the things that
所以背痛很可能也会成为被它改善的问题之一，
it eliminates, so...
也就是说，它可能真的能把背痛消掉……
Uh, that would be amazing.
呃，那就太惊人了
Yeah, for sure.
对，绝对是
For sure. Honestly,
真的 老实说，
the average happiness level for humans
如果只是把背痛这件事解决掉，
would just go up tremendously
人类整体的平均幸福感
if you just solve back pain,
都会大幅上升，
because it's not a question of
因为这已经不是
if you'll get back pain—it's when.
你会不会背痛的问题，而是你什么时候会背痛
You know you'll get back pain.
你知道你迟早都会碰到背痛
I...
我……
I keep on saying it's not a good design.
我一直都觉得，这种人体设计真的不太行
I keep on inviting you to come down to Fountain Life in
我一直邀请你来 Dallas 的 Fountain Life，
in, uh...
也就是，呃……
in Dallas. We'll, uh...
在达拉斯 我们会，呃……
we'll help you out sometime, when you have time.
等你有空的时候，我们可以帮你看看
Okay, well—
好吧，那——
do you have—like, what do you...
你们有——比方说，你们会怎么做……
I understand, like,
我知道，比方说，
you can get, like, MRI and CAT scans and everything,
你们可以做 MRI、CAT 扫描之类的各种检查，
but, like, what do you do with that?
但接下来呢？你们会怎么处理？
You know, it's like—
你知道，我的意思是——
Happy to send you the list.
我很乐意把清单传给你
I'll DM you the list of therapies or something.
我私讯把治疗方案清单之类的传给你
Yeah, exactly.
对，没错
Ha ha.
哈哈
Uh...
呃……
You know, um...
你知道，嗯……
Listen, you've been so generous.
听著，你今天已经非常慷慨了
Next up on stage with me
接下来要跟我一起上台的，
is another great moonshot entrepreneur,
是另一位非常厉害的 moonshot 创业家，
Ben Lamm, who runs Colossal—
也就是 Colossal 的创办人 Ben Lamm——
the de-extinction company, uh...
那家「物种复活」公司，呃……
you know, the woolly mammoth and 15 other species.
像是长毛象，还有另外十五种物种
I heard, yeah.
我有听说，对
I heard you say you might want a mini woolly mammoth.
我听你说过，你可能想养一只迷你长毛象
Is that true?
那是真的吗？
Yeah, I think it would be really cool to have a pet
对啊，我觉得如果能养一只宠物型的——
miniature woolly mammoth. That would be pretty epic.
迷你长毛象，真的会超酷，超传奇
Okay, I'll—
好，那我——
I'll put in a word for you with, uh...
我帮你跟，呃……
with Ben.
跟 Ben 提一下
That'd be adorable—little things just running around,
那一定超可爱，小小一只到处跑来跑去，
trumpeting away, and it's like,
还会不停发出象鸣，然后你就会觉得，
look at that, this is a great little pet.
你看，那真是超棒的小宠物
Amazing.
太棒了
And also, I—
而且我还想说——
can somebody please do Jurassic Park in real life?
拜托谁能不能把《侏罗纪公园》在现实中做出来？
Yeah, well...
对啊，嗯……
I'd definitely go, even if there was some risk of death.
就算有一点死亡风险，我也一定会去
It'd be super cool.
那真的会超酷
I think if anybody is going to do that,
我觉得如果真有人能做到，
it's, uh...
那肯定就是，呃……
it's Ben Lamm and Colossal.
Ben Lamm 和 Colossal 这组人马
He's engineering living life forms.
他是在设计活生生的生命形式
Someone asked him recently if he can make a Pikachu,
最近还有人问他，能不能做出一只皮卡丘，
and he said, "Probably."
而他居然回答说：「大概可以 」
Yeah.
对
Well, Jurassic—
嗯，侏罗纪——
Jurassic World, whatever.
《侏罗纪世界》也好，总之都行
That would be great. All right.
那会太棒了 好吧
I'll ask him, yeah.
我会去问问他，对
Elon,
Elon，
so grateful for you coming and joining us and sharing.
真的非常感谢你今天来到现场，加入我们，并分享这些想法
Thank you, my—
谢谢你，我的——
thank you, my friend.
谢谢你，我的朋友
Let's give it up for Elon Musk.
让我们把掌声送给 Elon Musk